Guide to the Gay Men's Health Crisis records
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
- Series XVI. AudioVisual Department, 1985-1999, n.d.
  - XVI. B. Departmental Productions
    - XVI. B. 2. Development Department
      - You Gotta Have Friends, undated; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
        16mm negative dailies called "You Gotta Have Friends" CR 56-62 Exterior shots of Tisch building Fragment Fragment of Tisch building dedication Interview with Legal Services staff member Part 2 Sync
    - XVI. B. 3. Education Department
      This subseries contains audiovisual material produced for the Education Department and consists of video and audio tapes created to educate clients about HIV/AIDS, treatment options, and other issues facing PWAs. This subseries is divided into six sections, each containing programs designed for specific populations.
      Beyond 2000 (B2K) was a sexual health program and survey that recruited 2000 gay men, regardless of HIV status, in volunteer efforts to help uninfected gay men stay free of HIV as the 21st century approached. Gay Men of African Descent (GMAD) includes interviews with African American men with substance abuse issues. House of Latex videos contain footage of events thrown by the ballroom and vogueing community as well as interviews with community members. Safer sex productions, which are explicit in content, were produced to demonstrate that sensuality need not be sacrificed for safety. Also represented are productions geared specifically to women including client and staff interviews and footage from the Multicultural HIV Prevention for Women Conference. Young adults are also represented in this subseries. Highlights are Youth at Risk, a production that contains interviews with youth activists and footage from the Conference of Peer Educators (COPE), and It is What it Is, a film geared towards teenagers that addressed sexuality, homophobia, and safer sex.
      - Beyond 2000 (B2K)
        - B2K, ---; 7 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Cypress and Sava interview, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Drew interview and Negative condom wrapping group #1, Apr 24; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Larry and Phillip, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Gay Men of African Descent (GMAD)
        - Black History Month, 1998; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - GMAD rough, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - GMHC GMAD, undated; ---; 9 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Paul Darling, 1995 Apr 6; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - House of Latex
        - Balls, 1994 Jun 4
          - House of Latex Ball, 1994 Jun 4; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - House of Latex Fun Ball, 1994; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - House of Latex Halloween, undated; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - Having Fun Never Has To End, 1994; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          - House of Latex House of Exotique, undated; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - House of Latex Jordan Ball, 1994 Jun 6; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - House of Latex Jordan Ball, 1994 Jun 4; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          - House of Latex Princess Ball, undated; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - House of Latex SUCE Fashion Show, ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - PSAs
          - Fraternity, Have Fun All Summer Long, The Package That Is, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          - Having Fun Never Has to End, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          - House of Latex, undated; ---; 7 videocassettes (unavailable)
          - House of Latex - Be Safe All Summer Long, 1995 Oct 19; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          - Program 3 GMHC "Youth", House of Latex, Mission Nutrition PSAs, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Safer Sex
        - Car Service, 1989; 1089; 2 videocassettes (1 of 2 unavailable)
        - Chance of a Lifetime/Grey Hideaway, 1985; 1097, 1098; 2 videocassettes
          A music video using footage from Chance of a Lifetime. Music by Richard Bone. AIDS prevention feature dramatizing scenarios of various explicit safer-sex practices.
        - Current Flow, 1989; 1092; 1 videocassette
        - Latino Safer Sex Video, 1993 Apr 30; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Law and Order, 1989; 1091; 1 videocassette
        - Midnight Snack, undated; 1090; 1 videocassette
        - Mist Behavin, 1989 Jun 1; ---; 5 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - S &M], undated; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Safer Sex Comix, 1988 Dec 30; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Safer Sex: The Time is Now, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Something Fierce, 1989; 1088; 1 videocassette
        - Steam Clean, undated; 1096; 1 videocassette
        - What Next?: A Story of Sex in the 80s, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          The fictional account of Mark, an illustrator who learns about safer sex as he draws illustrations for a safer sex comic. Written and directed by Paul Zakrzewski
      - Women
        - Barbara Naeff, 1988 Dec 17; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - FPWA dancing, undated; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Group #2, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Lesbian support Project Connect, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Mothers Group, undated; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Project Connect, 1990; ---; 5 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Sunny Rumsey, undated; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Women and AIDS forums, 1997 Feb 21; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
        - Women and AIDS Teach In, undated; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - Young Adult
        - El Puente, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
          Fictionalized account of hispanic teenage couple negotiating safer sex.
        - It Is What It Is..., 1992; 1056; 1 videocassette
          Fictionalized group of teenagers discussing sexual identity, homophobia and safer sex practices. Produced by Gregg Bordowitz
        - Teens Tell the Facts, 1989 Feb 4; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        - Youth at Risk, undated; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
          Interviews with youth activists from Youth Teaching Youth About AIDS and footage from the Conference of Peer Educators (COPE)
    - XVI. B. 4. Evaluation Research
      This subseries contains three videorecordings of presentations given by researchers who worked in conjunction with the Evalutation Research Department.
      - Community Disintegration and the Spread of AIDS, 1996 Jul 24; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        Dr. Mindy Fullilove
      - HIV Testing, AZT Use/Treatment Decision Making, 1996 Mar 27; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
        Dr. Karolynn Siegel
      - Methodology at the Margins, 1996 Jun 26; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
        Rebecca Young
    - XVI. B. 5. Substance Use Counseling and Education Program, ---
      SUCE materials includes audiovisual material produced for the SUCE program and contains interviews with both staff and clients of the program as well as footage of support groups that were aimed towards women, lesbians and African American men. The material includes raw footage of these interviews and groups that were edited for the final productions.
      - Ana & Carolyn, undated; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - Ana Oliveira Interview, 1995 Apr 28; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Bang Bang, 1993; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Edith Springer, undated; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - G &L Substance Abuse Interviews, undated; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - GMAD SUCE, 1995 Apr 20; ---; 5 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - HIV Positive Support Group, 1995 Mar 11; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - Interview with Walt Odets/Edith Springer, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Luis Palacios-Jimenez Drug Seminar, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Men HIV Support Group, 1995 Mar 29; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Photos for Substance Abuse, What about Gay Bars, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - Recognizing and Assessing Drug Abuse, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      - SUCE HIV Negative, undated; ---; 6 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - SUCE Lesbians, 1995 Jun 20; ---; 7 videocassettes (unavailable)
      - Walt Odets, 1995 Apr 27; ---; 6 videocassettes (unavailable)
  - XVI. C. Oral Histories
    Richard Dunne created the oral history program at GMHC in the late 1980s in order to document the history of the organization and its role in the AIDS crisis. Dunne was an avid historian who recognized the importance of the historical record for future understanding of events. He realized the importance of GMHC and wanted to ensure that its history was not lost. He encouraged surviving founders, early members, and others to record their roles and memories of GMHC through this program.
    Interviewees include founders Larry Kramer and Lawrence Mass, and early volunteers, board members, and staff members Bob Cecchi, Richard Dunne, Dick Failla, Rodger McFarlane, Enno Poersch, and Mel Rosen.
    - Barr, David, 1988 Mar 30; 964; 1 videocassette
      Interview with David Barr, Associate Director of Policy, then Director, late 1980s - 1996. (Second tape of interview)
    - Beckham, Dixie, undated; 967A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Dixie Beckham, longtime volunteer therapist.
    - Behrman, Lori, undated; 971; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Lori Behrman, Assistant, then Director of Communications, 1985-[1990?].
    - Bruce Beckwith, undated; 978; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Bruce Beckwith, longtime volunteer buddy and team leader beginning in the early 1980s
    - Callen, Michael, 1988 Jun 30; 950A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Michael Callen, HIV Antibody Positive Project
    - Casserta, Tony, undated; 965A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Tony Casserta, volunteer early 1980s. (Second tape of interview)
    - Cecchi, Bob, undated; 947A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Ombudsman, 1985-[1990?]
    - Craig, Mimi and Martin Telfer, 1997 Oct 14; 973; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Mimi Craig and Martin Telfer: Mimi worked in Development in the late 1980s; Martin worked in Facilities in the early 1990s.
    - Cutler, Mitchell, undated; 963A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Mitchell Cutler, volunteer early 1980s.
    - Davidson, Barry, undated; 966A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Barry Davidson, Director of Hotline, then Director of Administration, early 1980s - 1990.
    - Dunne, Richard, undated; 952A-D; 4 videocassettes
      Interview with Richard Dunne, Executive Director, 1985-1989.
    - Failla, Dick, undated; 946A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Dick Failla, Board Member, 1982-[1990?]. Failla was the first openly gay judge on the Supreme Court of the State of New York.
    - Feinbloom, Sandy, undated; 949A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Sandy Feinbloom, Deputy for Programs 1985-[1988?]
    - Hollabaugh, Amber, undated; 972; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Amber Hollibaugh, Education, Lesbian AIDS Project early 1990s.
    - Jacobs, Raymond, undated; 958A-C; 3 videocassettes
      [1990?]. Interview with Raymond Jacobs, Education Department, Prevention. Early 1980s-
    - Kendler, Helen, undated; 979; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Helen Kendler, Client services, case manager, late 1980s-2000.
    - Kolodner, Nathan, 1989 Jun 1; 961A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Interview with Nathan Kolodner, Board President, 1986-1990.
    - Kramer, Larry, 1990 Jul 25; 955A-E; 5 videocassettes
      Interview with Larry Kramer, Founding Board Member
    - Lipner, Jay, 1988 Mar 31; 969A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Jay Lipner, longtime volunteer lawyer.
    - Mass, Larry, undated; 944A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Interview with Larry Mass, Founding Board member.
    - Mattes, Jed, 1991 Mar 19; 968A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Interview with Jed Mattes, longtime volunteer lawyer, early 1980s-[1990s?].
    - McFarlane, Rodger, undated; 943A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Rodger McFarlane, Executive Director, 1982-1983
    - Palachios, Luis, undated; 1070A-B; 4 videocassettes (2 of 4 unavailable)
      Interview with Luis Palachios in the hospital. Volunteer therapist, 1980s.
    - Paschek, Joe, undated; 962; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Joe Paschek, Board member 1982-.
    - Patterson, Bruce, undated; 976; 1 videocassette
      Bruce Patterson was Hotline Director from the late1980s through the late 1990s.
    - Patterson, Bruce and Amini, undated; 977; 1 videocassette
      Bruce Patterson was Hotline Director from the late 1980s through the late 1990s. Amini was assistant to the Deputy for Programs beginning in the early 1990s.
    - Poersche, Enno, undated; 959A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Enno Poersch, Board member, 1982-
    - Quadland, Michael, 1990 Mar 23; 960A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Interview with Michael Quadland, volunteer therapist early 1980s.
    - Rosen, Mel, 1989 Nov; 957A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Interview with Mel Rosen, Executive Director, 1984-1985.
    - Sample interview, undated; 951; 1 videocassette
    - Senack, Mark, 1988 Apr 21; 948A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Interview with Mark Senack, Director, Legal Services, 1985-1990
    - Soref, Jeff, 1994 Jul 13; 954; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Jeff Soref, Board President, 1990-1993.
    - Stone, Krishna and Stephen de Francesco, 1997 Oct 14; 975; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Stephen de Francesco (continues from 00974) and Krishna Stone. De Francesco was Director of Publications, 1986-2000.
    - Sweeney, Tim, 1993 Jul 21; 956; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Tim Sweeney, Deputy for Policy, 1986-1989; Executive Director, 1990-1993.
    - Tausig, Doris, 1990 Mar 19; 970; 1 videocassette
      Interview with Doris Tausig, Hotline volunteer, early 1980s.
    - Vitale, Silvia Witts and Stephen de Francesco, 1997 Oct 14; 974; 1 videocassette
      continues 00975). Vitale was a client advocate during the early 1990s. De Francesco was Director of Publications, 1986-2000. Interview with Silvia Witts Vitale and Stephen de Francesco. (Francesco interview
    - Wein, Ken, 1988 May 11; 945A-C; 3 videocassettes
      Interview with Ken Wein, Client Services, early 1980s.
  - XVI. D. PSAs
    This subseries contains public service announcements (PSAs) produced for various departments. Included here are PSAs for fundraising events; programs aimed at women, Latinos, and transsexuals; safer sex awareness; and other topics.
    - Celebrity PSAs, 1986 Dec 10; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - GMHC Womens Open House PSAs, 1997 Nov 1; ---; 3 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - Keith Haring animation PSA, 1991 Sep 27; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
    - New York Talks AIDS 95, 1994 Dec 16; ---; 5 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - Operation Speakout, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
    - Projecto Popi, Latex Towel, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
    - Transisters, undated; ---; 4 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - Vito DeSario, undated; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - Women's Education Services PSA and Soulfood PSA, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
  - XVI. E. Miscellaneous
    This subseries contains miscellaneous productions of the Audiovisual Department that do not fit into any of the above series or were collaborations between GMHC and other organizations,. Included are interviews with participants in Project Connect, New York City's first mental health and substance abuse program for gay men and lesbians sponsored by the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual & Transgender Community Center, and the Fortune Society, a program for currently and formerly incarcerated individuals. There are interviews with serodiscordant couples (couples in which one partner is HIV positive and the other is HIV negative) that were conducted for I Love Her Just the Same, I Love Him Just the Same. Also included are memorial services of notable GMHC staff members and other AIDS activists and a tribute video to volunteer Judy Peabody and GMHC's 10th Anniversary video.
    - Act Up- Stonewall Anniversary March, 1989; 1331; 1 videocassette
      ACT UP/New York illegally marches from Sheridan Square (West Village) up 6th Avenue to Central Park for the 1989 Stonewall Anniversary.
    - Act Up- Target City Hall demonstration, 1988 Mar 24; 1322, 1326; 2 videocassettes
      Contains ACT UP poster-making party with Larry Kramer; civil disobedience training session; and ACT UP pre-action meeting for Target City Hall Demonstration The second ACT UP action at Wall Street on the first anniversary of the original Wall Street action.
    - Arthur Bernstein, M.D. talk], 1987 Nov 20; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      On love and death.
    - Craig Harris Memorial, undated; 1027, 1028, 1029; 3 videocassettes
      Craig Harris memorial reflections by numerous people including Robert Penn and Tim Sweeney, with footage of Harris. Craig Harris reading from The Road Before Us at Tower Books.
    - Deadlier than the Virus, 1991; 1052; 1 videocassette
      Condom over Jessie Helms's house by TAG (Treatment Action Group). Video by Robert Hilferty and Robert Huff.
    - Fast Trip, Long Drop, 1993 Oct 8; 1301; 1 videocassette
      A personal 54-minute feature film by Gregg Bordowitz juxtaposing the filmmaker's Jewish family heritage and values with his diagnosis as a person living with AIDS.
    - Fortune Society, 1994 Jan 26; ---; 10 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - I Love Him Just the Same, I Love Her Just the Same, 1995 Oct 6; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
      Interviews with male and female serodiscordant couples.
    - Judy Peabody Tribute, 1995 Dec 12; ---; 2 videocassettes (unavailable)
    - Mildred Pearson Memorial], undated; 1049; 1 videocassette
      At a Mother's Love meeting.
    - Nathan Kolodner Memorial, undated; 1030; 1 videocassette
    - Needle Exchange Trial, 1991; 1327A-B, 1335A-B, 1336, 1337A-B; 7 videocassettes
      Trial court footage of AIDS activists arrested for distributing clean needles to IV drug addicts. Documentation of the complete trial was organized by activists in the Needle Exchange Committee of ACT UP/NY. Testimonies by Zoe Leonard and Gregg Bordowitz.
    - New York Citizen's AIDS Network Conference, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
    - Ojos Que No Ven..., undated; 1095; 1 videocassette
      Produced by LUCES (Latinos Unidos Contra el SIDA) and Gay Men's Health Crisis. Includes PSAs with John Robles and Jose Serrano.
    - Paul Popham Memorial, 1987; 1048; 1 videocassette
    - Rafael Tavares Memorial, 1989 Mar 21; 1031; 1 videocassette
      Rafael Tavares, M.D. memorial videotape. A presentation of the HIV Center For Clinical and Behavioral Studies.
    - Sonia y Edwin, undated; ---; 1 videocassette (unavailable)
      Couple receiving counseling on AIDS diagnosis. Spanish language film. Girl on bike Leticie and Juan in the park
    - Thinking about It with Richard Dunn, undated; 953A-B; 2 videocassettes
      Press conference with Richard Dunn with question and answer session.